<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter written to a Christian friend, and one of the Parliament men. Proposing the groundlesness of the plea for tyths, impropriat [sic] tyths, or tyth as a revenue due to the magistrat.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04013</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1767A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R179629</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51571978</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51571978</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175279</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04013)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175279)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2726:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter written to a Christian friend, and one of the Parliament men. Proposing the groundlesness of the plea for tyths, impropriat [sic] tyths, or tyth as a revenue due to the magistrat.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed the sixth day of the tenth month, in the year of our Lord 1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  England --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Taxation --  England --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Taxation of personal property --  England --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175279:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER Written to a Chriſtian Friend, and one of the Parliament Men. PROPOSING The groundleſneſs of the <hi>Plea</hi> for TYTHS, impropriat TYTHS, or TYTH as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue due to the Magiſtrat.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſalm 119. verſe 128.</bibl>
               <p>Therefore I eſteem all thy Precepts concerning all things to be right, and I hate every falſe way.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <head>FOR THOV SHALT LABOR</head>
               <p>PEAC PLENTIE</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed the ſixth day of the Tenth Month, in the year of our Lord 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:175279:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere are Reaſons not expreſſed, why this Letter was printed: and did you know what muzing thoughts (in the ſolitary night) I had, and what pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſighes went from my heart, deſiring God to ſpeak me ſilent; becauſe being no party that pay or receive Tyth: and how I have objected, that I am no man of power in the Nation, and that I minde things too high for me, and am unprofitable to Church or State, and a Veſſell but for mean uſe, and that needs muſt I erre, being no Maſter-builder: Yet conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again, the Great <hi>Potter</hi> of the Earth hath made me for ſome End, I dare not but move as I am move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: the dumb Aſs was not to be ſmitten when not faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Thus praying you, that what you finde rude and weak in theſe enſuing Lines, that charge on mee as mine, but what you finde of Truth and Juſtice there, that is my God's, and thy God's, to whom I commit thee and all the Flock of Chriſt. And that you may reade without prejudice, I ſhall conceal my Name, not fearing who can blot it if written in the <hi>Lamb's</hi> Book of Life.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175279:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honorable Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Salutacion of him that is unworthy greets you, and preſuming on your unfeigned love to the Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and all his Saints, I do write theſe; and that you ſhould not want encouragement in this Work of the Lord now called to, I ſhall tell you, the prayers and breathings of the hearts of Gods Saints are, that you may do worthily, and much for Gods honor; &amp; firſt be as zealous for the Sons honor as the Son was for his Fathers. See you not the pollutions of the Land? how baſe and wicked men make merchandiſe of the Word of the Lord, and preach in the Name of the Lord, when the Lord never ſent them! that know nothing of the operation of the Spirit by which the Word ſhould be publiſhed! theſe dumb Souls, I hope you will finde ſomewhat like the Rods of ſmall Coards to drive them out, for they have no part nor fellowſhip in this buſineſs, well you may call them your Servants and Hierlings, but <hi>Chriſt</hi> owns them not, they never came in by the Door, wherefore their work, and your care, and wages for them, ſhall be all ſet down for nothing in the laſt Account; why hear you not the bleatings of of the flocks, that cry, Take away theſe Wolves, that rob us at your pleaſure!</p>
            <p>You tell us dear Friend, the Knot of Tyth you cannot undo, now the Lord God and Father of <hi>Ieſus</hi> be with you, and teach you to work in your work: I preſume you are not left to ſerve alone, for the Father of Spirits is with you. Sir, I believe the fooliſh things of this World ſhall ſtand and confound the wiſe, and I do here preſume you will ſuffer a Fool gladly, becauſe you are wiſe. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I cannot believe Tyths are now to be practiſed, for it was the <hi>Iews</hi> Law, proper to them onely, becauſe no where commanded but in the Ceremonial Law, and there was for divers uſes, whereof God provides for himſelf a Sacrifice, the firſt born: the <hi>Levites</hi> had no other Portion nor Inheritance amongſt their Brethren but Tyths; the Prieſts were to have ſome certain Fleſh, the firſt fruits, and for Purification; alſo the Poor, the Strangers, Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175279:3"/>and fatherleſs, were fed of the Tyths, and theſe with other Ceremonial worſhip were Types and Shadows of glorious things to come, and to be fulfilled by our great High Prieſt <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and therefore 'tis clear, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.12. the Prieſthood being changed, there is a neceſſity of changing that Law, it was not Moral; God never commanded <hi>Abraham</hi> to give the Tenth, nor <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> did not demand it, but the Text ſayth, <hi>He gave the Tenth;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> when they proſpered by the Sword, they ſhared the Spoil to thoſe which remained at home, as well as to thoſe that went to war. Now we finde it caſt out of the <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> and diſuſed among the <hi>Chrſtian</hi> Churches in the Primitive time, and of a truth it will and muſt follow, they were brought in by <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> or ſome tyrannical Prince for him, and was diverted from Monks and Friers to Biſhops and Deans, and then to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Miniſtry, and now ſome would have it for a Goſpel-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry; but ſhall that which was for the moſt part, yea I may ſay altogether raiſed by the <hi>Pope</hi> the <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and impoſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Popiſh Laws, Councils, and Parliaments, and was an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> for his worſhip, and is this day one of the Crutches he leaneth on in <hi>England:</hi> ſhall this poor Inheritance crept out of <hi>Babel,</hi> be divided amongſt them all? Muſt all ſhare of it? No, let every one have his right, let the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, Miniſter, and Worſhipers take what pertains to them; and the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrate, Miniſter, and Worſhipers, take what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to them: we are not of the entailed Heirs of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> we drink not all of one Rock, we have ſworn and covenanted with and before the high God to reſiſt in our Places all Popery and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Innovations, in Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline. Now ſome ſay they were of free Gift, but prove that: perhaps ſome were, but moſt was impoſed, and that was to an idolatrous uſe, and therefore it was ill done to give, and worſe to force it from men, for who required it at their hands? alſo it is an unjuſt Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, there is no Calling pays like the Farmer, although there are rich moneyed men, great Merchants and Tradeſmen in the Land far-way abler, yet pay little or nothing; alſo ſome Land pays nothing at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, and other Lands which pay Tenths, which many times amounts to three parts of the Rents, are cozened, and pay the Tenth of all their ſtock every year, not laying by his Seed eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry year, which he payd the Tenth of the year before; the Law gave but the Tenth of the Increaſe; alſo you have the Tenth of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175279:3"/>the Sheep, and the Tenth of the Wool of the nine that remained; therefore this will bear the name of a cruel curſt Law: by this means they bear dominion over us, and the Yoak is heavier upon that Calling than all others, contrary to the Apoſtles Rule, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.13. neither is it that others ſhould be eaſed, and you grieved; how like <hi>Iews</hi> do we look, with our Oblations, Tyths, and Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings! Are we in carnal <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſtill, or coming toward <hi>Mount Sion</hi> that new <hi>Ieruſalem?</hi> Surely we are on our way, then ſtand by you Tithes, you are not of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Men fear, and care, and conclude no Miniſtery, nor worſhip of God can be maintained without them. We never reade nor finde any of theſe uſed in <hi>Chriſts</hi> and his Apoſtles times, and yet Gods worſhip purely main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and therefore carnal fears, and it being <hi>Iewiſh,</hi> Popiſh, and unjuſt, undenyably I ſhall beg, that as you gave it not its birth, ſo let it have neither breath nor being.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, It is unjuſt, Impropriators ſhould loſe their Purchaſe. Indeed it is a very proper name, and ſuits their Title well, it is fitly ſo called, and were his Holineſs the Pope now keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing houſe here in <hi>England,</hi> he would ſoon curſe all ſuch Children, as have committed ſuch Sacriledg, as thus to rob his Church. It is unjuſt for any man to pay any, therefore unjuſt for him to force to pay or receive any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it was never raiſed at the firſt to put in his Purſe, he doth nothing at all for it, therefore no ſhadow of truth in it why he ſhould enjoy it; it was firſt unjuſtly raiſed, then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from the uſe given, and ſtill is unjuſtly payd, and never will be juſt till it go back to the Landlord, who is the tru Owner there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for he bought the Land, and if any Commodity be found in the Land, and Purchaſe, more than the Seller and Purchaſer were aware of, whoſe is it but the Purchaſers? as in all other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts and Bargains we take them at all adventures, ſomtimes they prove better, ſomtimes worſe than expected.</p>
            <p>Again it will be ſayd, then you will wrong, and perhaps undo many, who have bought ſuch Impropriat Tithes, and payd largely for them. Indeed we fear many are wronged, but who hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them? Not you, the Keepers of our Libertyes, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Juſtice: your duty is to defend the good and clear Title, and not elſe: neither hath the Seller, for the Title was well known to be what it is, a Badg of Tyranny, for ſo <hi>Samuel</hi> perſwades <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. to avoyd that tyranny, and have no King, [for he will have the Tyth of all, and it ſhall be for a Judgment, ye ſhall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175279:4"/>cry out in that day becauſe of your King. In <hi>Henry</hi> the third's time there was granted to him two ſhillings out of every Plough-land, and in another Kings Reign there was granted the Eights of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry City and Burrough, and Twelfths out of the Countrey; and is any grieved, becauſe this being eſtabliſhed by a Law, is layd aſide? Whether did King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth alienate Tyth, or take it away by Law or not? We affirm Kings at their Coronation are ſworn to govern according to Law; why were not Monopolyes and Ship-money willingly received under our late King? No, we cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out he was a Tyrant, ruling by a Prerogative Power. Was not King <hi>Henry's</hi> Act the ſame? he was in a rage, and had a luſt to do what he did, and ever ſince Cuſtom and the gain thereof hath cauſed that unlawfull Act to ſtand in force, and therefore why ſhould not all the Patentee-men be ſatisfied? King <hi>Charls</hi> had as much Law on his ſide as King <hi>Henry;</hi> it is the duty of a Subject of a Nation to know the Laws thereof, that they may be ſure to have Law on their ſides, for want of the knowledg hereof many have loſt thouſands of Pounds, and for redreſs have thrown hundreds after, and what recompence ſhould theſe men have? Surely none, unleſs they can ſummon their Deceivers to keep a Court of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. And for Impropriators, I am not againſt their having ſome ſatisfaction, it is but Equity and Juſtice, they ſhould have ſome recompence, but not from them which have not hurt them, unleſs they will; I wiſh they may finde good mercifull men: and if it were a forced Salary at the firſt, it being unequal for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion with other mens Eſtates, and unjuſt, becauſe ye received the Tenth of the Increaſe, and the Tenth of the Stock, as was made appear, and becauſe it was gathered to uphold a Popiſh wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, it ought to fall with the worſhip: again, grant it were a free Gift at the firſt, and ſuppoſe all to be in the Donors power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow, (which I do queſtion, how he could give any other than his own, <hi>viz:</hi> the Tenth of his Land,) yet being taken away from the uſe for which it was given, and converted to no ſuch end, but ſold away for gain, &amp; imployd to particular mens benefit; this implyes the Donor had no Power, yea, was not capable of a Gift, if he were capable to give a Gift, &amp; ſuch a Gift, then that Gift was lawful, and then who had power to ſell ſuch a Gift, and divert it from that uſe? but if the Magiſtrat ſay, the uſe was unlawfull, then I ſay the Gift was an unlawfull Gift, and the Boons return from whence it came. Indeed it is unavoidable, ſome late Purchaſers will be Loſers by it,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175279:4"/>unleſs the Charity of the men of the place, or the Seller, or the State, will as an Act of their Grace and Mercy give ſome Gratuity to ſuch as have little elſe, which they are to acknowledg to be a free Gift if they receive any thing, but ſome have kept it long, and bought it for a ſmall matter, and have ſo employd it, that when they give it back again; it will not ow them a Penny: alſo this ſort of men or the greateſt number of them will be Gainers in their other Land more than this comes to if Tyths fall, and indeed they muſt &amp; will fall ere long, and I perſwade my ſelf if the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will not honor themſelves ſo far as to throw them down, the People will diſhonor themſelves ſo much as to pay them with great unwillingneſs. We are declared to be a free Nation, and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat profeſſing to take off all burdenſom Yoaks, whereof <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet cals this one in the place before named; and theſe are they that eat the fat and beſt fruit, in many places, they have the chief Tyth, and perhaps the Miniſter hath left him ſome Tyth Egs, and the reſt of all the ſmall Tyth, not enough to maintain many of them in a mean ſort.</p>
            <p>And for encouragement to all Impropriators, conſider I pray you what <hi>Amaziah</hi> did, 2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 25. he made but a bad Bargain to loſe his money, and have nothing for it, becauſe willing to take counſel of the Lord; ſo do ye, reſtore back again, openly, rather than wrong thy ſelf and neighbour by a Law; I would have them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what that Traitor <hi>Judas</hi> did, read you never, after he was convicted of ſin, taking unlawfull wages for unlawfull work, ſayth he, <hi>Take the thirty Pieces of Silver again:</hi> But it is affirmed by ſome the national Miniſters have an equitable and unqueſtionable right to Tyths as any man hath to his Free-hold, (but I think they are deceived) ſee <hi>Fox Acts and Monuments, Volume</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 604, 632, 669. <hi>and he that robs them in Tyths and Offerings may as well take away any mans Free-hold.</hi> I take it a man holds his Free-hold either by Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe or Gift, or is Heir by deſcent, but they cannot claim Tyths as that they bought them, nor yet of Gift, (<hi>Antichriſt</hi> was no ſuch Benefactor to raiſe them, and give it to any other than the Brats of his own breed) and a ſtrange thing it is, how it ſhould come to them by deſcent, for ſure they are not all of one ſtock; but haply the Magiſtrat having long accuſtomed himſelf with old Idolaters and Tyrants, and living with them, might obſerve their manners, and at laſt divide the Prey as well as others before, as it is ſayd of the two ſons of <hi>Joſias, Ezek.</hi> 19. <hi>being nouriſhed among the Lions whelps they became as Lion:.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:175279:5"/>
            <p>Indeed I may ſay, though there be much Rubbiſh of the Romiſh Kirk caſt out, yet <hi>all the High places</hi> are not quite taken away, and though Tyths have been confirmed by Popiſh Parliaments, and the Kirk (ſo called) who have been Lords Paramount in <hi>England,</hi> for many years, and ſo would not let their glory fall: alſo by others who have ſhared the Spoyl with them, whoſe Intereſt hath been as ſweet to them as their Perogative: I ſay, what if theſe have kept up the old Cuſtom, yet this lets not, but a Chriſtian Magiſtrate may and ought to take down all the high Places that remain. <hi>O fooliſh Generacion, why count ye it an hard thing to caſt out Tyths!</hi> have you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to ſay more why this ſhould not ceaſe, but only your Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs and Cuſtom? I preſume you will not in other Caſes plead, that Cuſtom gives a clear Right and Intreſt, for then thoſe that have accuſtomed themſelves to ſteal, may plead Cuſtom to be a Law for them; and he that hath received a guift, may plead it is a duty for the Donor to give another guift: indeed you make ſuch a Smoak with your Arguments, as have put out and blinded the eyes of many, and made many look as it were a-ſquint. The Prophets are bid to cry aloud againſt the Abominacions of the Times, Iam no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, nor prophets Son, yet I am bold to perſwade you to do what you can to caſt out Baal, and all the Idols thereof, and <hi>Curſed is he that doth the work of the Lord negligently.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any ſhall maintain Tyths to be a loſt Inheritance, and would make uſe of <hi>Num.</hi> 5.8. for a recovery, and to be dedicated to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry for the Service of the Lord: Iſhall anſwer, this inſtance is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper; firſt becauſe the Text ſpeaks of a wrong done, a ſin or treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs againſt any man, for that is implied; ſome man muſt be wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but who is wrong'd here, or what Miniſter of <hi>Chriſt</hi> can chalenge Tyth to be his, and if none be wronged, none ought to be offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if taken away, and then there is no Sin or Treſpaſs committed: but if you ſay they are the Magiſtrates, then what need you ſtrain ſo far to bring a loſt Law, to make it a loſt Inheritance? for the Law was Ceremoniall in every branch of it: firſt there is required Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucion with the Principal, a recompence of the Treſpaſs, and a fifth Part added; now what Law of God that is Morall requires any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Reſtitucion, according to the nature of the offence, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times bare Reſtitucion, ſomtimes four-fold, ſomtimes ſeven, but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucion of principal Dammage, and a fifth Part added is Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, if not why do not all Offenders add the fifth Part. Secondly to be payd to the uſe of the Preiſts for the Service of the Lord, but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175279:5"/>now there is no ſuch Subject or Object, the Preiſt-hood is fallen, and we look for one to come. Thirdly, Reſtitucion was not, nor could not be made without the <hi>Ram</hi> for Atonement, for the Text ſayth, beſides the <hi>Ram</hi> for Atonement: I know it was practiſed by the mother Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when any man dyed Inteſtat, the <hi>Pope</hi> poſſeſſed himſelfe of all the Eſtate.</p>
            <p>Tythes are not ſo Civ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll as ſome men account; they were ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from common uſes, and conferred upon the Church, becauſe the Tenth was counted holy; and whether it was done by the Pope or ſome towardly Son of his, and their ingenious Councill, yet it was their vain Superſticion to divert this holy Tenth to the Church, becauſe now no expreſs Stipend or conſtant Salary is allotted ſince the Jewes Law for the Service of the Lord, and to keep up worſhip, what God required in one Generacion he required not in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for worſhip: how differently was God well pleaſed in the ſeverall Ages of the world! in <hi>Abels</hi> time before the Floud, and <hi>Abrahams</hi> time, it was different from <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Solomons</hi> time, and that different from the Apoſtles and Primitive time; the firſt Fruits of Sheep that would ſerve in one Age, was not enough in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Age, with the Tenth and Redempcion of the firſt-born, and daily Sacrifice, but abundance muſt be added for the Tabernacle, and Temple work, in its time, and for the Church in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, you know all theſe chargable Sacrifices were too little: <hi>Chriſt</hi> tels the young man <hi>he muſt ſell all: Zaccheus gave halfe of his goods,</hi> and Scripture ſayth, <hi>many that had Lands and Poſſeſſions, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Price of them, and layd it at the Apoſtles Feet,</hi> becauſe of the need: we proporcion our Contribucion by our Civ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll Law, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the eſtate and condicion of the Object, and we ſhould lay out towards the Worſhip of God, that that Worſhip might be maintained in honour, by all that count it their honour to have a right worſhip; and this is to be obſerved, every one to miniſter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what a man hath, keeping this in your Eye, the flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtate of the Church, and thoſe that miniſter there: ſometimes the condicion of the Church may be ſuch, that the hundredth part of a mans Eſtate layd out in Gods Cauſe and Worſhip, may be an acceptable Sacrifice, and again at other times 3 parts of 4 will not be ſufficient; from whence you may conclude, that Tyths, Tenths, or a certain Stipend, enjoyned every man toward the Service or VVorſhip of the Lord, is not the way of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and if you would not count me proud, I would challenge you for an Inſtance from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175279:6"/>the Sciptures, where the Magiſtrate was to uſe his Coërcive Power, for the VVorſhip of God; but the Prophets did acconut them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed if they obſerved not all the Commands of God to do them: Yet are Chriſtian Magiſtrats an unſpeakable Bleſſing in a Land, and the age paſt would have found it ſo, could the Flock of <hi>Chriſt</hi> but have eſcaped with their Lives out of the hands of thoſe Wolves; we enjoy more; they are a Refuge to keep off the Storms, they caſt out and abhor Idolatry, and falſe worſhip, and are Tender of all that fear our God, yea the Church may ſay, behold the Magiſtrate is one with us, he hands along with her; therfore my prayer is, that as he hath companied with her in the wilderneſs, and hath lent her his help in an untrodden way, amongſt vaſt and terrible Eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that he will travell with her till they both come to their Reſt, and certain it is, there is a Reſt for the People of God, and then I dare ſay, I know who will pay them for all: the truth is, <hi>Antichriſt</hi> put into <hi>England</hi> to advance his Throne and worſhip, and to that end muſt have this maintenance; now we renounce <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> &amp; his way, and reſolve, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> being upon his Throne, ſhall rule us in his way: then Judg the caſe, while we lived under <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> Magiſtrates, we could expect no other Laws, but ſuch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ad, therefore muſt ſuffer his manners; and whether be forced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w, or became a Lying-Spirit, to ſeduce for Pollitick ends, and ſo raiſed his maintenance, by threatning damnacion to the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant world, if they dedicated not their holy Tenths to ſuch a uſe: yet muſt this ſtand as the Lawes of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> faſter than all other Lawes that hath been found, not according to the word of God, and ſo repealed by the Reformers of theſe Times: Statutes of Princes were no excuſe to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to follow, but they were reproved for obſerving them, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.16. Methinks I hear ſome of the Conſciencious Miniſters ſay, I wiſh the firſt fruits were down, that is a little too ſuperſticious; and I dare ſay, if they knew how to ſignifie ſo much to you without weakning the whole Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion, you ſhould quickly hear of ſome humble Peticioners: but if I might be the Judge, I ſhould condemn none, if they paſs by all ſuch kinde of Devocion: ſome counted it a great Loſs when Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polizers and their patents were caſt out, but the Voyce of them that rejoyced, was greater than the Cry of thoſe that mourned: why halt ye between God and <hi>Baal;</hi> let us chuſe him that is God, and follow him: doth any particular man loſe a Juſt and Lawfull Inheritance, if taken away? why then I Oppreſs no man if I with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175279:6"/>my Tything, and then what command of God is broken?</p>
            <p>If Tythes fall, the Nacion in general wil gain it, the Landlord and Tenant wil ſhare it, and of theſe two ſorts the whol Land al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt conſiſts; and theſe are they, with the Souldiery, that under God have redeemed the Nacion from <hi>Antichriſts</hi> yoak, <hi>for who goeth to warfare on his own coſt?</hi> Moneys and Treaſures are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſinews of War, by it they have redeemed our Government and Laws, and if there come any right of gayn therby, let them ſhare in it: But I wonder ſome of our enemies have gone but an equal ſhare with us that have born the brunt, and heat of the day! This <hi>Act of Oblivion</hi> hath bin like <hi>Agags</hi> ſparing many of the fat cattel; me thinks Subſidies on ſome men would do well, <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> in Math. 17. conclude from whom the Princes of the Earth take Tribute or Pole-money. But to our Queſtion, Every family, perſon, ſubject, high or low, muſt lay out for the worſhip of God, as God commands; but if we give away our Tythes, which is the Commonwealths and Nacions in general, hereby, and then the Commonwealth eſpecially, the poor Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords and poor Tenants, wil be the more diſabled, and out of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to lay out for the worſhip of God, which he requires of them. You wil ſay, the Magiſtrat ſhould diſpoſe of it. I ſay, God requires every man that he diſcharge his duty in the worſhip of God: and I ſay, how can many people do any thing when the Magiſtrat hath robd us of ſo much of our ſubſtance? I wil appeal to Chriſtians, if they have faith enough to beleeve, in every age that the Magiſtrat wil employ the Commonwealths ſubſtance al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to the glory of God, his worſhip, and the relief of the Saints; perhaps this Magiſtrat may, but haply the next may be as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that knew not <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> that wil not know the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> and ſhal we now put our necks under their feet, and deſire them to boar us thorough the Ear for ever! No, if this be a Chriſtian Magiſtracy, let them take of us what the ſtate and condicion of affaires cals for, and what God requires of them. If this be not a time, under a Chriſtian Magiſtrat, to proclaym Liberty from <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> when then! The Jews had a Law, if a man ſould his Inheritance, and were not able to redeem it,<note place="margin">By Scripture account <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> is a nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</note> he ſhould ſtay but untill the year of <hi>Jubile,</hi> the fiftieth year, and then it ſhould return to the ſame Family again for nothing: we have had a generacion that have taken away our ſubſtance, good and pleaſant things, for 7 hundred years together, and we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175279:7"/>it again with our Blood and Treaſure; and ſhall not we keep our <hi>Iubile</hi> yet! then be ye boared thorough till the End of all things.</p>
            <p>But to purſu all your benighted Queſtions; Suppoſe Tythes were given, the tenth of a mans Land to the Popiſh Prieſt, and all the holy Order created Officers by a Papal power,, Antichriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Supream in that Throne: I ſay, admit they were given to their Uſe, and the Uſe of the poor, as Writers make it appear they were. Now the poor have been diſ-inherited wrongfully, for our Saviour ſayth, <hi>the poor yee have alwayes with you,</hi> but that Order of Officers (created as aforeſayd) ought to have no room nor ſtanding in the Church, as ſubjects fit to receive the ſame: And as it is with an Annuity, payable out of a mans Land, it is payable no longer than ſuch perſons to whom it was given, live to receive it; the Land may be often ſould, and the Annuity payd ſtill, but at laſt it fals into ſome of their hands for want of heyrs: I ſay, the Officers aforeſaid are, &amp; ought to be caſt out, &amp; no other by the Laws of the Land can chalenge Tyth, but ſuch as have bin ſealed with the Mark of the Beaſt, aforeſayd: So that to me it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, if the State charge this Land with the paying of Tyth, it muſt be by a new Impoſt: It is not the wages the Goſpel Miniſters can chalenge, it may be inſufficient, or too much for Goſpelers to offer in Faith. And as for the poor, the Laws of the Land have provided that they be maintayned according to their need: And as for a Stock to maintayn Wars, and Negotiations with other Nacions, as a Treaſury for the Magiſtrate, for State Affaires; this ſhould be rayſed according to occaſion: therfore if Tyth ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main payable, and the uſe be ceaſed, then the little finger of our Magiſtrat will be heavier than our fathers loyns, our fathers bore the woodden yoak, and we the yron.</p>
            <p>And now I beſeech you (dear friend) in the bowels of the Lord <hi>Ieſus,</hi> miſtake me not, as if by this I would overthrow the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, a thing my ſoul abhors, but my prayers are that God would purify <hi>the Houſe of Levi,</hi> and that <hi>all the Prophets of the Lord may be holy.</hi> Oh, ſhall I deny that which is of God! God forbid: I know the Miniſtry to be an Ordinance of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13. and I hope I ſhall never live to deny the leaſt Ordinance of God; I had rather paſs to the Grave and there reſt in ſilence, than to have my Name ſtand among that proud Generacion: I know it was the fruit of Chriſts Interceſſion, to ſtore the Church with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175279:7"/>guifts for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, that is, the Church: and the faithfull Miniſters of the Goſpel have a precious luſtie &amp; comlineſs in my ey, eſpecially thoſe that love the work for their Maſters ſake, I mean the converſion of ſouls; I ſay their employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the moſt honourable, they ſerve the Lord Chriſt: <hi>They that convert ſoules to God ſhall ſhine as the Starres in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> they are fathers in the Church; and it may ſerve to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, that God hath appointed this way, <hi>to teach men by men.</hi> And my prayer to God is, that he would ſend out? more faithfull Labourers, for the harveſt is great. Alſo <hi>Maintenance</hi> for them is as clear an Ordinance as the other; I could inſtance in many Scriptures, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. and the beſt of outward things befits the beſt Calling, and not nigardly porcions; for they muſt uſe Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, and ſo be Enſamples for their flock, and for a Chriſtian Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion ſo profeſſing to be; tis not our glory but our ſhame to let them live beggerly, and in diſgrace; as we flouriſh, they ſhould be partakers: he that gives freely and of a chearfull minde, he offers the acceptable Sacrifice to God, and none is accepted for Sacrifice but ſuch. Our Saviour ſayth, <hi>the time ſhall come, that he that worſhipeth, ſhall worſhip in ſpirit and in truth:</hi> but you wil ſay, who ſhal take care for the worſhip of God, Miniſters, and Maintenance, in the mean time? That I ſuppoſe is your work to be ſtudying how to be nurſing fathers to the Church, and to ſee that thoſe that preach and publiſh the Goſpel under your Dominion, may have du encouragement and ſupply; I think none wil deny but that they ſhould participate with us in our good and pleaſant temporall things, and I judg it better by guift than force: in the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> they gave all things as they had them for building the Temple and Sacrifice: the Apoſtle tels <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias, was it not in thy power?</hi> Acts 5.4. The portion God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the <hi>Levites</hi> as it was typicall, ſo to encourage them in the work, ſo that being about the work of the Lord, they might not be hindered: and the mayntenance Miniſters ſhould receive beſides as duty from the Donor, it ſhould be for encouragement to him whoſe work is enough for the whole body and minde: is it any encouragement to a ſervant to continu his ſervice, that muſt ſu for his wages after earned by painfull ſweatings and hard labor? is it any encouragment to the Merchant and Tradeſman, after they have made uſe of their utmoſt skill in buying, and wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to take the beſt ſeaſon for Winde and Tide to bring home their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175279:8"/>Goods, and after all muſt impoſe them on ſuch as will never pay till haled to Priſon, this ſpeaks the Commodityes to have no worth in them; ſo for the Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to have their Wages by force, and to be a man of ſtrife when his Meſſage is Peace, and precious work, it is I ſay for him to force, and become a Ruff-man: Can he do this and be encouraged in his work? the Word ſayth alluding to them, <hi>The Labourer is worthy of his hier;</hi> ſo that the Goſpel is of ſome worth; and O that the Goſpel might diſſolve hard hearts more; many times it proves but ſouer Food to eat the Bread of him that hath an evil eye, yet many have their teeth fet on edg.</p>
            <p>I wiſh theſe faults were amended, the covetouſneſs of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters leſs, and the Charity of the People more. I know no Rule in the Word of God, that the Magiſtrat ſhould ſtudy wholly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the Miniſter from living ſomwhat by Faith: now how far a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrat may force worſhip, and for worſhip in every <hi>Punctilio</hi> I will not diſpute, but this I know, Goſpel Principles bears, that every man do what he do in Faith: and this I know is according to the Law of Nations, if the Magiſtrat command any thing againſt my conſcience, I ought to obey or ſuffer; I will not undertake to ſay what the Magiſtrate may not do as a Magiſtrat, but I conceive this he may do without oppreſſing any, give to the Miniſters the Glebe Land in all places, alſo all thoſe Lands wreſted out of the Biſhops hands, for whatſoever we won by conquering our late Enemy, and not ſold in the three Nations, is in your power to give or ſell, and much more: were I a Stateſman (pardon the ſuppoſal) I ſhould bend my minde to finde out to ſerve the Church, and bring my glory to her; and if there were fewer fixed Miniſters in moſt parts of the Downs, and thoſe places and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes where there are few Inhabitants joyned, and an itinerat, godly, and able Miniſtry to journey from place to place, it may probably awake the deaf and dead ſinners more; and O that they might hear the voyce of the Son of God and live; but if they will not hear nor receive them, to turn away. But Sir, want I Bowels or Expreſſions, the deareſt Lord knoweth I ſpeak the truth in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I ly not, for it pierceth my heart as ſharp arrows, to think that Gods Labourers (for ſo they are called) ſhould toyl all the day of their Pilgrimage, praying, and woing men in <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſtead that they would be reconciled to God, and while they are telling them the good tidings of the Goſpel, and counſelling and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:175279:8"/>pointing out to the fooliſh world <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which is the tru Bread come down from Heaven, and for all this men have no bowels moved, to count them worthy of common Bread; my heart pityes all hard hearts, and all hearts bound up, whom their own ey does not pity. Let them know, Mercy is but Mercy in its time, and then Juſtice ſeals what Mercy leaves: O you precious hearts! conſider your labor ſhall not be loſt in the Lord; Can you ſpend and be ſpent for the Lord <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Remember who ſayth it, <hi>I will never leave you, nor forſake you:</hi> Do not think you ſerve an hard Maſter: Can you believe the Children of the Earth will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor you with what is theirs? <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſayth, <hi>The world loves its own, and if ye were not the Children of the Light, the world would not hate you;</hi> I know no Rule they have to match the world ſo well as this, ye ſtand by Faith in the greateſt Peace and Proſperity that can be, you are at uncertaintyes with the world, how long you ſhall ſtand, or when you ſhall fall; Remember <hi>Chriſts</hi> Kingdom <hi>is not of this world,</hi> therefore poſſeſs all you have or would have by Faith, and it is not long but <hi>he that ſhall come will come, and bring his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with him;</hi> but wo to thoſe whoſe Gold and Silver is cankered through ignoble imployment, for the Ruſt of it ſhall witneſs againſt them. <hi>Dives</hi> hath his place. I have nothing more with you for the preſent, for I know not how you can bear this: In the mean time you may be ſure, I honor your Authority, your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, your Perſon, and ſo commit you to the Eternal God, and ſtil remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors in all humble and du obſervance.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
